Guide to the Montana Military Veterans Oral History Project 1993-2002
Montana Historical Society Research Center
1993-2002
Montana Historical Society, Research Center Archives Archives 225 N. Roberts PO Box 201201 Helena MT 59620-1201 (406) 444-2681 mhslibrary@mt.gov
Montana Military Veterans Oral History Project
Montana Historical Society
Sound Recording
109 interviews
Number of pages in transcript or summary provided in container list
This oral history collection records the experiences of Montanans in all branches of service and from various military campaigns; including World War I, World War II, the Korean War, Vietamese Conflict, and the Persian Gulf War.
Project History
From World War I through the Persian Gulf War, Montana has ranked in the highest percentile nationally in the number of its citizens serving as military personnel. These numbers include nearly 5,000 women since 1940 and as well as a substantial number of Montanan tribal members. Montana played a significant role in American military strategies during the Cold War, due to the presence of Malmstrom Air Force Base and its numerous missile silos. This project was started in 1993 to record the experiences of those who served in the military forces and the families and communties who were impacted by the service.
This project consists of 109 interviews recording the experiences of Montana's veterans, with discussions of families, precombat training, service on the home front and overseas, returning to civilian life, career military life, and feelings about military conflicts.
Inventory is arranged by item, with each oral history interview listed by its unique OH number. An abstract for each interview is provided in the inventory to allow keyword searchability. The abstract includes the number of cassettes, CDs and/or transcript pages for the interview, as appropriate. Researchers requesting copies of interviews should refer to the OH number when ordering.
Restrictions, if applicable, are indicated within specific oral history descriptions.
Interviews in the collection conducted by Montana Historical Society Staff or volunteers
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Research Center catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
United States Armed Forces; United States. Army; United States. Air Force; United States. Navy; United States. Marine Corps; United States. Coast Guard; United States. Army. Infantry Regiment, 163rd; World War, 1914-1918; World War, 1939-1945; Korean War, 1950-1953; Persian Gulf War, 1991; Vietnamese Conflict, 1961-1975; Camp Rimini War Dog Reception and Training Center; First Special Service Force; Women veterans; Native American veterans; Prisoners of War; Veterans
Montana
Montana; Oral Histories; Sound Recordings; Military
- JOHN TERREO INTERVIEW, OH 1195; 2 tape(s), Transcript 50 pages
  John Terreo (b. 1954) discusses his work as a civilian employee with the U.S. Navy during the early 1970s; the 20th Century Montana Military Veterans Oral History Project; uses of oral history in documenting contemporary historical events. Interviewed by Roy Caldwell, April 14, 1993, Helena, MT.
  Restriction: RESTRICTED UNLESS PERMISSION GRANTED BY INTERVIEWEE
- DAVID C. THOMAS INTERVIEW, OH 1197; 2 tape(s), Transcript 39 pages
  David C. Thomas discusses his experiences in Operation Desert Shield/Storm as a member of the Montana Army National Guard's 103rd Public Affairs Detachment attached to the 3rd Armored Calvary Regiment. Interviewed by John Terreo, March 19, 1993, Fort Harrison, MT.
- NEELIAN NELSON AND MARGARET NELSON INTERVIEW, OH 1198; 2 tape(s), Summary 4 pages
  Neelian Nelson (b. 1915) discusses his early life in Wisconsin; experiences as a U.S. Army officer assigned to the Camp Rimini Dog Reception and Training Center during World War II; other military assignments. Margaret Nelson discusses her family and early life in Wisconsin; and experience as an army officer's wife at Camp Rimini. Interviewed by John Terreo, February 2, 1993, Missoula, MT.
- SUSAN GIBB INTERVIEW, OH 1199; 2 tape(s), Summary 4 pages
  Susan Gibb (b. 1946) discusses her family and growing up in Hysham, Montana; education and employment as a school teacher in Washington; enlistment and career as a United States Air Force officer. Interviewed by John Terreo, February 2, 1993, Missoula, MT.
- EMIL CHRISTIANSEN INTERVIEW, OH 1200; 1 tape(s), Summary 2 pages
  Emil Christiansen (1893-1991) discusses his experiences with the Montana Army National Guard on the Mexican border in 1916; service with U.S. Army medical company in France during World War I; and activities with the Montana National Guard following the war. Interviewed by Phil Curry, December 12, 1987, Fort Harrison, MT.
- DAVID SAYRE INTERVIEW, OH 1219; 1 tape(s), Transcript 19 pages
  David Sayre (b. 1948) discusses the mobilization of the Montana Army National Guard's 103rd Public Affairs detachment and departure for Operation Desert Shield/Storm; the unit's mission, and his responsibilities; service in Vietnam with the United States Marine Corps; nuclear, chemical, biological warfare training; work with the Great Falls Tribune; views on the Iraqi invasion of Kuwait and the United States response. Interviewed by John Terreo, December 9, 1990, Fort Harrison, MT.
- PATRICK MOHAN INTERVIEW, OH 1220; 1 tape(s), Transcript 14 pages
  Patrick Mohan (b. 1948) discusses his service with Montana Army National Guard 103rd Public Affairs Detachment; duties, responsibilities, and position within unit; concerns of operating sensitive video equipment in a desert environment; civilian employment as special education teacher; being mobilized for Operation Desert Shield/Storm; interacting with a very different society; rules imposed on U.S. military personnel by Saudi Arabian government; and reasons for U.S. military presence in the Middle East. Interviewed by John Terreo, December 9, 1990, Fort Harrison, MT.
- ROY CALDWELL INTERVIEW, OH 1221; 1 tape(s), Transcript 16 pages
  Roy Caldwell (b. 1953) discusses his reasons for joining the Montana Army National Guard; military service with United States Air Force and Montana Air National Guard; his duties and responsibilities in the 103rd Public Affairs Detachment; mobilization for Operation Desert Shield/Storm; concerns over the operation of a dark room in desert environment; rules of conduct for U.S. military forces in Saudi Arabia; the reasons for military response; and cooperation of his civilian employer. Interviewed by John Terreo, December 9, 1990, Fort Harrison, MT.
- KAREENE OSTERMILLER INTERVIEW, OH 1222; 1 tape(s), Transcript 21 pages
  Kareene Ostermiller (b. 1957) discusses the mobilization of the Montana Army National Guard's 103rd Public Affairs Detachment for Operation Desert Shield/Storm; describes unit's mission; her response to the invasion of Kuwait by Iraq; her experiences with Montana Air National Guard and as first woman aide-de-camp to Montana Army National Guard's State Headquarters; discrimination encountered in service; concerns about family and living in different environment; and dealing with another culture and its treatment of women. Interviewed by John Terreo, December 9, 1990, Fort Harrison, MT.
- TERRANCE M. YOUNG INTERVIEW, OH 1223; 1 tape(s), Transcript 17 pages
  Terrance Young (b. 1942) discusses his service with the Naval Reserve in the 1960s; reasons for joining the Montana National Guard; service with a tank unit in Shelby, Montana; assignment to the 103rd Public Affairs Detachment; duties and responsibilities within unit; civilian occupation; affects of crisis on employer and family; primary mission of the 103rd; and views regarding U.S. involvement in Persian Gulf region. Interviewed by John Terreo, December 9, 1990, Fort Harrison, MT.
- CHARLES "MILO" MCLEOD INTERVIEW, OH 1224; 1 tape(s), Transcript 15 pages
  Charles "Milo" McLeod (b. 1947) discusses service in the U.S. Army's 173rd Airborne Brigade in Vietnam in 1969; joining Montana Army National Guard in 1976; mobilization of 103rd Public Affairs Detachment for Operation Desert Storm/Shield; the U.S. response to the invasion of Kuwait by Iraq; the Total Force concept; employment with U.S. Forest Service and its cooperation with the National Guard; family concerns; and differences between the Gulf Crisis and the Vietnam War. Interviewed by John Terreo, December 9, 1990, Fort Harrison, MT.
- TODD BUHMILLER INTERVIEW, OH 1225; 1 tape(s), Transcript 18 pages
  Todd Buhmiller (b. 1963) discusses joining Montana Army National Guard; the mobilization of 103rd Public Affairs Detachment for Operation Desert Shield/Storm; the function of the unit and his personal responsibilities; cooperation received from employer, Montana State University, regarding his activation; the Soldiers and Sailors Act; Nuclear, Biological, Chemical warfare (NBC); and the U.S. response to Iraqi invasion of Kuwait. Interviewed by John Terreo, December 9, 1990, Fort Harrison, MT.
  Restriction: RESTRICTED UNTIL PERMISSION GRANTED BY INTERVIEWEE
- GREG FOX INTERVIEW, OH 1241; 1 tape(s), Transcript 15 pages
  Greg Fox (b. 1953) discusses why he enlisted in the Montana Army National Guard; his posting to the 103rd Public Affairs Detachment in 1985; the function of unit and its responsibilities; the mobilization of the unit for Operation Desert Shield/Storm; his civilian employment; the Gulf crisis and the U.S. response to it; concerns over unit's equipment in a desert environment; rules Saudi Arabia imposed on U.S. military forces; the petroleum industry; and family matters. Interviewed by John Terreo, December 9, 1990, Fort Harrison, MT.
- PATRICK HERMANSON INTERVIEW, OH 1242; 1 tape(s), Transcript 14 pages
  Patrick Hermanson (b. 1951) discusses his service with the U.S. Army's 656th Air Defense Artillery Battalion and 7th Infantry Division during 1970s; joining the Montana Army National Guard; his posting to 103rd Public Affairs Detachment as commanding officer; the mobilization of his unit for Operation Desert Storm; his civilian employment; the U.S. response to Iraq's invasion of Kuwait; unit's mission; concerns as commanding officer; and family members. Interviewed by John Terreo, December 10, 1990, Fort Harrison, MT.
- JODIE YELTON INTERVIEW, OH 1243; 1 tape(s), Transcript 9 pages
  Jodie Yelton (b. 1944 or 1948) discusses his reasons for joining the Montana Army National Guard; his posting to 103rd Public Affairs Detachment; the mobilization of his unit for Operation Desert Shield/Storm; dealing with another culture; the U.S. military presence in Saudi Arabia; the function of the unit and its reponsibilities. Interviewed by John Terreo, December 10, 1990, Fort Harrison, MT.
- ANDY LEE JOHNSON INTERVIEW, OH 1244; 1 tape(s), Transcript 9 pages
  Andy Lee Johnson (b. 1968) discusses the mobilization of the Montana Army National Guard's 103rd Public Affairs Detachment from Fort Harrison, Montana for Operation Desert Shield/Storm. He describes the unit's mission; his job assignment; and his feelings and observations regarding U.S. response to invasion of Kuwait by Iraq. Interviewed by John Terreo, December 10, 1990, Fort Harrison, MT.
- DUANE LONGFELLOW INTERVIEW, OH 1246; 2 tape(s), Transcript 40 pages
  Duane Longfellow (b. 1971) discusses his early life in Helena, Montana; basic training experiences as a U.S. Air Force recruit in Lackland, Texas; special training as an Air Force Security Specialist; training in Air Base Ground Defense; possible assignment to the Middle East for Operation Desert Storm; personal feelings regarding the U.S. presence in that area; and other related issues. Interviewed by John Terreo, January 17, 1991, Helena, MT.
- MARY FELDER INTERVIEW, OH 1250; 3 tape(s), Transcript 60 pages
  Mary Felder (b. 1918) discusses her early life in Savannah, Georgia and Butte, Montana; her uncle, Pat Felder, who began the Postal telegraph in Helena; her nurse's training and education; work as a private duty nurse in Townsend and Helena; experiences as one of the first stewardesses for Western Airlines during the late 1930s; service as a nurse aboard hospital ship U.S.S. Bountiful during World War II; employment with Navy Relief Society; and work as a real estate agent in Helena during the 1970s. Interviewed by John Terreo, March 3, 1991, Columbia Falls, MT.
- LARRY LONGFELLOW INTERVIEW, OH 1251; 2 tape(s), Transcript 36 pages
  Larry Longfellow (b. 1945) discusses growing up in Helena, Montana; enlisting in the United States Navy in the early 1960s; basic training in San Diego, California; experiences as a helmsman on the cruiser U.S.S. Galveston (CG-1); fire support missions along Vietnam coast during mid-1960s; rescuing downed pilots; ports of call; Captain (later Rear Admiral) Alexander Goodfellow; and the Vietnam conflict and Operation Desert Shield/Storm. Interviewed by John Terreo, March 22, 1991, Helena, MT.
- JUANITA COOKE INTERVIEW, OH 1252; 1 tape(s), Transcript 21 pages
  Juanita Cooke (1910-1998) discusses her early flying experiences in California; acquiring a pilot's license; the Japanese attack on Pearl Harbor and restrictions placed on non-military flights; her recruitment into the Women Air Force Service Pilots (WASPS), 1942-1944; primary, basic, and advanced flight training and living conditions at Advenger Field, Sweetwater, Texas; aircraft she flew; ferrying fighter aircraft to various bases in the United States including Great Falls, Montana. Interviewed by John Terreo, March 27, 1991, Helena, MT.
- ERNEST FACHNER INTERVIEW, OH 1253; 1 tape(s), Transcript 25 pages
  Ernest Fachner (b. 1925) discusses his experiences as an infantry soldier with the 24th Army Division in New Guinea and the Philippine Islands during World War II; living and combat conditions; and basic training at Camp Roberts, California. Interviewed by John Terreo, April 7, 1991, Lewistown, MT.
- TERRANCE E. PERRY INTERVIEW, OH 1254; 1 tape(s), Transcript 18 pages
  Terrance E. Perry discusses his service with the United States Marine Corps from 1942 to 1946 including basic training and medicial air evacuation missions in the Central Pacific; United States Air Force at Malstrom Air Force Base, Great Falls, Montana from 1947 to 1949; Marine Corps Reserves from 1950 to 1958; Montana Air National Guard from 1963 to 1966; United States Naval Reserve as a recruiter from 1967 to 1976; retirement; and his views on the Persian Gulf War. Interviewed by John Terreo, March 2, 1991, Columbia Falls, MT.
- HUGH CLIFFORD CUMMING INTERVIEW, OH 1255; 2 tape(s), Transcript 43 pages
  Hugh Clifford Cumming (b. 1926) discusses growing up in Philipsburg, Montana; early education; service with the United States Marine Corps during World War II, including basic training at San Diego, California and Browning Automatic Rifle Training at Camp Elliot, California; life aboard troop ships; experiences on Guam and Iwo Jima with the Marine Division as part of a mortar squad; earning the Bronze Star; the American Legion; veterans and veterans benefits; and conflicts following World War II. Interviewed by John Terreo, June 26, 1991, Helena, MT.
- ORVILLE QUICK INTERVIEW, OH 1256; 2 tape(s), Transcript 53 pages
  Orville Quick (b. 1922) discusses growing up in Nebraska and moving to Montana; joining U.S. Army 29th Engineers in 1940; military induction process and basic training at Oceanside, California; service in Hawaii; the Japanese attack on Pearl Harbor; amphibious landings, fighting, and airfield construction on Pacific islands of Baker, Makin, and Saipan; destruction of Japanese aircraft by U.S. P-61 night fighters; living conditions while on islands; mass burials of Japanese soldiers; capture of Japanese civilians; encounters with U.S. Construction Battalions (CeeBees); troop transports; and views on later U.S. military conflicts. Interviewed by John Terreo, June 20, 1991, McCone County Museum
- LARRY KILMER INTERVIEW, OH 1257; 2 tape(s), Transcript 53 pages
  OLarry Kilmer (b. 1952) discusses growing up in Helena, Montana; enlisting in the U.S. Coast; training experiences; duty assignments in Alaska and Washington; experiences in the drug war aboard Coast Guard Cutters U.S.S. Lipan and U.S.S. Confidence Guard; and the role of Coast Guard in Operation Desert Storm/Shield. Interviewed by John Terreo, July 10, 1991, Helena, MT.
- KERMIT EDMONDS INTERVIEW, OH 1258; 3 tape(s), Transcript 70 pages
  Kermit Edmonds (b. 1938) discusses his experiences in the U.S. Army; participating in Operation Desert Shield/Storm as a member of the Montana Army National Guard's 103rd Public Affairs Detachment; and views on war. Interviewed by John Terreo, February 13, 1992, Missoula, MT.
  Restriction: ACCESS RESTRICTED: Researchers may contact narrator directly
- FRANK LAWLOR INTERVIEW, OH 1259; 1 tape(s), Summary 1 pages
  Frank Lawlor briefly discusses his service with the United States Air Force; employment with the U.S. Department of Agriculture; life in Kalispell, Montana; and the Montana Veterans Home. Interviewed by Raelyn Olsen, May 23, 1991, Columbia Falls, MT.
- GERALD R. BENTLEY INTERVIEW, OH 1260; 1 tape(s), Summary 1 pages
  Gerald R. Bentley briefly discusses his two years of service in the U.S. Army. Interviewed by Shane Bidwell, May 9, 1991, Columbia Falls, MT.
- LEE J. CORWIN INTERVIEW, OH 1261; 1 tape(s), Summary 1 pages
  Lee J. Corwin briefly describes his service with the United States Air Force guarding military aircraft in Vietnam and later assignments in the Phillippines and Guam; retirement; and move to the Montana Veterans Home. Interviewed by Chuck Peterson, May 10, 1991, Columbia Falls, MT.
- ROY HOELKE INTERVIEW, OH 1262; 2 tape(s), Transcript 58 pages
  Roy Hoelke (b. 1918) discusses his family and childhood in Wisconsin; education at the University of Idaho; visits to Sanders County, Montana; service in the Reserve Officer Training Cadet (ROTC) program during World War II; service with the Army Air Force 389th Heavy Bombardment Group in the European Theatre of Operations as a bombadier on a B-24 heavy bomber; heavy bomber strategy and tactics; military training at San Antonio (Texas) Aviation Cadet Center; and later life. Interviewed by John Terreo, July 22, 1992, Helena, MT.
- HENRY ZIMMERMAN INTERVIEW, OH 1263; 1 tape(s), Summary 1 pages
  Henry Zimmerman, born in Great Falls, Montana, earned a degree in agriculture economics and served in the United States Air Force and the National Guard. His father worked on a cattle ranch as a bookkeeper at Malmstrom Air Force Base Interviewed by Lavon Habets, June 6, 1991, Columbia Falls, MT.
- JAMES E. HARPER INTERVIEW, OH 1264; 1 tape(s), Summary 1 pages
  James E. Harper discusses his service with the United States Army during World War II; and his experiences with medics, artillery, and tank destroyers. Interviewed by Alicia Huff, June 6, 1991, Columbia Falls, MT.
- PHILIP SMITH INTERVIEW, OH 1265; 1 tape(s), Summary 2 pages
  Philip Smith (b. 1908) discusses his service with the U.S. Navy Sea Bees during World War II and life in Kalispell, Montana following the war. Interviewed by Jill Daugherty, May 16, 1991, Columbia Falls, MT.
- CARSON WALKS OVER ICE INTERVIEW, OH 1266; 2 tape(s), Transcript 51 pages
  Carson Walks Over Ice, a resident of Crow Agency, Montana discusses the warrior traditions of the Crow tribe; enlisting in the U.S. Army; basic and airborne training; his combat experiences in Vietnam as a U.S. Army Ranger; efficiency of the North Vietnamese Army; and his homecoming. Interviewed by John Terreo, August 5, 1992, Little Big Horn College, MT.
- MICHAEL A. SANDERS INTERVIEW, OH 1270; 1 tape(s), Summary 4 pages
  Michael A. Sanders (b.) discusses his experiences as an infantry soldier during Operation Desert Shield/Storm. Interviewed by Nestor Aurita, March 24, 1992, Missoula, MT.
- DOROTHY ANNE DAVIS FORRESTER INTERVIEW, OH 1271; 2 tape(s), Transcript 47 pages
  Dorothy Forrester (b. 1919) discusses her family; early life in Dillon, Montana; education; and working with the American Red Cross during World War II. Interviewed by Lee Graves, April 15, 1992, Dillon, MT.
- ROY WILLIAM FORRESTER INTERVIEW, OH 1272; 2 tape(s), Transcript 48 pages
  Roy Forrester (b. 1919) discusses his family; early life in Dillon, Montana; service with the U.S. Army during World War II; and the Siapan Island campaign. Interviewed by Lee Graves, April 15, 1992, Dillon, MT.
- CARL M. DAVIS INTERVIEW, OH 1273; 2 tape(s), Transcript 42 pages
  Carl M. Davis (b. 1922) discusses his family and early life in Dillon, Montana; education; service with the U.S. Navy during World War II and the Korean War; and his experiences fighting in the central Pacific. Interviewed by Lee Graves, April 25, 1992, Dillon, MT.
- ROBERT D. ANDERSON INTERVIEW, OH 1274; 3 tape(s), Transcript 70 pages
  Robert D. Anderson (b. 1945) discusses his family; early life in Baldwin, Wisconsin; education; enlisting during the Vietnam War; service with U.S. Army in Vietnam; General William Westmoreland; drug use among U.S. troops; memories of Vietnamese people; and life after his discharge. Interviewed by Lee Graves, April 9, 1992, Helena, MT.
- RAY FITCHETT INTERVIEW, OH 1275; 1 tape(s), Transcript 23 pages
  Ray Fitchett (b. 1931) a resident of Heron, Montana discusses his early life; enlisting in the U.S. Marine Corps; basic training; service in the Marine Guard aboard the heavy cruiser U.S.S. Helena during Korean War; experiences as marine raider and spotter for warship gunfire support; getting wounded; meeting and guarding President Dwight D. Eisenhower; flying back to Montana with Goveror John Bonner and J. R. Wine, the mayor of Helena; and his life after leaving the military. Interviewed by Sara Lou Springer, May 14, 1992, Heron, MT.
- DORIS BRANDER INTERVIEW, OH 1276; 2 tape(s), Transcript 27 pages
  Doris Brander (1921-1995) discusses her service in the Womens Auxiliary Voluntary Expeditionary Service (WAVES) during World War II; her reasons for joining the WAVES; her wartime duties; life on the homefront; USO shows; Eleanor Roosevelt; minority women in the military; the 1930s Depression; attitudes towards women in the military; women's military memorial in Washington, D.C.; and life after military service. Interviewed by Rosetta Kamlowsky, June 11, 1992, Helena, MT.
- HELEN DAWSON INTERVIEW, OH 1277; 1 tape(s), Transcript 32 pages
  Helen Dawson discusses her experiences with the U.S. Navy's Women Accepted for Volunteer Emergency Service (WAVES) during World War II; serving as a navy storekeeper; duty at Alameda, California Naval Air Station and in Honolulu, Hawaii; and life after discharge. Interviewed by Rosetta Kamlowsky, June 11, 1992, Helena, MT.
- GENEVIEVE S. ADAIR INTERVIEW, OH 1278; 1 tape(s), Transcript 29 pages
  Genevieve Squires Adair (b. 1911) discusses her family and growing up in Plainview, Nebraska; relocating to Butte, Montana in 1916; attending the Normal College in Dillon; her enlistment in the Women's Auxiliary Army Corps (WAAC) in 1943; officers training; work classifying female recruits at Fort Des Moines WAAC training center; transfer to Fort Meade; black military personel; pay scale; nursing; life after military service. Interviewed by Rosetta Kamlowsky, July 29, 1992, Helena, MT.
- ELDORA MCBRIDE INTERVIEW, OH 1279; 1 tape(s), Transcript 26 pages